<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "tei_all.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Dubliners</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Alessandro Labate</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Project Gutenberg</distributor>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>The writers of Dubliners, by James Joyce</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
<!--ESERCIZIO PAG. 73-117: Marcare un testo plain text di circa 3000 caratteri a
piacere.-->
        <div n="ch1" type="chapter">
            <p>
            <head>THE SISTERS</head>
                There was no hope for him this time: it was the third stroke. Night
                after night I had passed the house (it was vacation time) and studied
                the lighted square of window: and night after night I had found it
                lighted in the same way, faintly and evenly. If he was dead, I thought,
                I would see the reflection of candles on the darkened blind for I knew
                that two candles must be set at the head of a corpse. He had often said
                to me: <q>“I am not long for this world,”</q> and I had thought his words
                idle. Now I knew they were true. Every night as I gazed up at the
                window I said softly to myself the word paralysis. It had always
                sounded strangely in my ears, like the word gnomon in the Euclid and
                the word simony in the Catechism. But now it sounded to me like the
                name of some maleficent and sinful being. It filled me with fear, and
                yet I longed to be nearer to it and to look upon its deadly work.</p>
                            <p>
                <hi rend="italic">Old Cotter</hi> was sitting at the fire, smoking, when I came downstairs to
                supper. While my aunt was ladling out my stirabout he said, as if
                returning to some former remark of his:
                <q>“No, I wouldn’t say he was exactly ... but there was something queer
                ... there was something uncanny about him. I’ll tell you my
                opinion....”</q>
                He began to puff at his pipe, no doubt arranging his opinion in his
                mind. Tiresome old fool! When we knew him first he used to be rather
                interesting, talking of faints and worms; but I soon grew tired of him
                and his endless stories about the distillery.
                <q>“I have my own theory about it,” he said. “I think it was one of those
                ... peculiar cases.... But it’s hard to say....”</q>
                He began to puff again at his pipe without giving us his theory. My
                uncle saw me staring and said to me:
                “Well, so your old friend is gone, you’ll be sorry to hear.”
                “Who?” said I.
                <q>“Father Flynn.”</q>
                <q>“Is he dead?”</q>
                <q>“Mr Cotter here has just told us. He was passing by the house.”</q>
                I knew that I was under observation so I continued eating as if the
                news had not interested me. My uncle explained to old Cotter.
                <q>“The youngster and he were great friends. The old chap taught him a
                great deal, mind you; and they say he had a great wish for him.”</q>
                <q>“God have mercy on his soul,”</q> said my aunt piously.</p>
                        <p><pb n="1"/>
                Old Cotter looked at me for a while. I felt that his little beady black
                eyes were examining me but I would not satisfy him by looking up from
                my plate. He returned to his pipe and finally spat rudely into the
                grate.
                <q>“I wouldn’t like children of mine,” he said, “to have too much to say
                to a man like that.”</q>
                <q>“How do you mean, Mr Cotter?”</q> asked my aunt.
                <q>“What I mean is,”</q> said old Cotter, <q>“it’s bad for children. My idea is:
                let a young lad run about and play with young lads of his own age and
                not be.... Am I right, Jack?”</q>
                <q>“That’s my principle, too,”</q> said my uncle. <q>“Let him learn to box his
                corner. That’s what I’m always saying to that Rosicrucian there: take
                exercise. Why, when I was a nipper every morning of my life I had a
                cold bath, winter and summer. And that’s what stands to me now.
                Education is all very fine and large.... Mr Cotter might take a pick of
                that leg mutton,”</q> he added to my aunt.
                <q>“No, no, not for me,”</q> said old Cotter.
                My aunt brought the dish from the safe and put it on the table.
                <q>“But why do you think it’s not good for children, Mr Cotter?”</q> she
                asked.
                <q>“It’s bad for children,”</q> said old Cotter, <q>“because their minds are so
                impressionable. When children see things like that, you know, it has an
                effect....”</q>
                I crammed my mouth with stirabout for fear I might give utterance to my
                anger. Tiresome old red-nosed imbecile!</p>
                        <p>
                It was late when I fell asleep. Though I was angry with old Cotter for
                alluding to me as a child, I puzzled my head to extract meaning from
                his unfinished sentences. In the dark of my room I imagined that I saw
                again the heavy grey face of the paralytic. I drew the blankets over my
                head and tried to think of Christmas. But the grey face still followed
                me. It murmured; and I understood that it desired to confess something.
                I felt my soul receding into some pleasant and vicious region; and
                there again I found it waiting for me. It began to confess to me in a
                murmuring voice and I wondered why it smiled continually and why the
                lips were so moist with spittle. But then I remembered that it had died
                of paralysis and I felt that I too was smiling feebly as if to absolve
                the <distinct>simoniac</distinct> of his sin.
                            </p><pb n="2"/>
        </div>
    </text>
</TEI>